Finding Aid for the John Allison Benjamin Papers Biomed.0001
UCLA Library Special Collections
- III.RESEARCH -- HISTORICAL & BIBLIOGRAPHIC
  - III A. HISTORY OF UROLOGY
    - "Anatomical and surgical restudy of Denonvilliers' fascia", 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      typed draft and reprint of paper by Charles E. Tobin and JAB, published in Surgery, Gynecology and Obstetrics, 80:373-388, Apr. 1945, plus correspondence; one illustration; see also Box 4-F4, F7 & F8
    - History of kidney anatomy, 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      material on an article under preparation, including correspondence (with J.B.de C.M. Saunders among others) concerning Fallopius, Monro, Mundinus, Portal, Vesalius, & Zerbi; photostat copies of pages from works by Johanni Beverovicio and Fallopius' Anatomical Observations, Cologne, 1562; a page from an Ifan Kyrle Fletcher rare book catalog; notes; illustrations of ontogenetic kidney development in human and of the nephron of the normal kidney; reprints by Donald O'Malley on Vesalian literature, Saunders & O'Malley on Vesalius, & of two William I. Straus, Jr. articles on Vesalius & on the primate kidney
    - History of kidney anatomy, 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      more material for an article under preparation, including mentions of Vesalius' kidney dissections; extensive copies & translations of works by M. Holl, Thomas Fahr, M. Staemmler, Richard Schmutzer, et al.; also a letter asking for permission to use plates from a Max Broedel paper; the original folder bore JAB's handwritten note "Vesalius, comment., etc."
    - "Hugh Young", 1945 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      reprint, galley proofs, & typed versions of obituary written by JAB, Science, 102(2652):416-417, Oct. 26, 1945; correspondence; additional obituaries & remembrances of Hugh H. Young, and two reprints of his articles; xerox of handwritten inscription "To Dr. John Benjamin with the kindest regards of Hugh H. Young, June 5, 1935"; brochures about Baltimore Lyric Theatre's golden anniversary (1944) and 25 years under the stewardship of the city's citizens (1945), with essays by Hugh H. Young, President of The Lyric Company, 1919-1945; for portrait, see Box 8-F25
    - Saliceto, Summa conservatiionis et curationis. Chirurgia, Induration of the kidney, 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      correspondence, mainly with Dorothy M. Schullian and Max H. Fisch of the Army Medical Library; translation of part of the Summa dealing with the kidney; photostat pages from the 1476 (?) and 1490 editions; illustrations; notes; translation of a paragraph of Aetius of Antioch, "Concerning the hardening of the kidneys"
    - "Observations on fused kidneys with horseshoe configuration: the contribution of Leonardo Botallo (1564)", 1947-1950 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      reprint & two typed drafts of an article by JAB & Dorothy M. Schullian, Journal of the History of Medicine, 3:315-326, 1950; used & unused illustrations, some mounted; correspondence; notes; photostat pages from various Botallo editions & an article by Saul Jarcho; one item transferred to Box 2-F6, another to Box 2-F7
    - Book review, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      draft and final copy of book review by JAB published in Bulletin of the History of Medicine, 36(6):580, Nov.-Dec. 1962, of: St. Peter's Hospital for Stone, 1860-1960, ed. by Clifford Morson. Edinburgh: Livingstone, 1960; letter of acceptance
    - "Abraham Colles (1773-1843), distinguished surgeon from Ireland", 1965 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      drafts & reprint of an article by JAB, Investigative Urology, 3(3):321- 323, 1965; correspondence; photocopies of Colles articles; obituary; notes; reprint of Tobin & JAB's article on fasciae from Surgery, Gynecology and Obstetrics
    - Thomas Addison, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      an article by JAB for the Dictionary of Scientific Biography; drafts, photocopies of material by and about Addison, and correspondence with J.G.E. Hopkins, editor of the DSB
    - Book review, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      drafts & reprint of book review by JAB published in Bulletin of the History of Medicine, 43(1):92-93, Jan.-Feb. 1969, of: Classical Articles in Urology, ed. By Mark A Immergut. Springfield, IL: Charles C Thomas, 1967; correspondence
    - Ureter cine paper, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      above heading on JAB's folder, plus: "Oct. 23rd 1969, Hist. Urol."; miscellaneous notes; a 1952 letter with bibliographic suggestions from Johan N. de Klerk
    - "Man and the ages judge this urine: macroscopic uroscopy before the eyes", 1970-1975 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      handwritten notes and supporting materials for a presentation to the American Urological Association, 1975; also includes a 24- page typed manuscript, "Pisse-prophets through the ages," by Martha T. Gnudi, 1970
    - The American Urological Association's The History of Urology, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      first plans for the above-named opus, which was finally published in 1976 under the title: Perspectives in Urology; JAB promised to provide two chapters, on anatomy of the genito-urinary system and on development of cine-radiography in urology; correspondence; "Table-of-Contents" and "Information for Contributors"; notes; reprints of all the Tobin & JAB articles on fasciae & other JAB papers (discarded by the preparator; other copies noted throughout the collection); seven reprints by various authors; this project continued in Box 2-F30, Box 3-F35, F38 & F41, and Box 4-F1, F2 & F3
    - The development of urological x-ray cinematography, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      drafts & final manuscript of chapter by JAB and Frank Hinman, forerunner of the Macintyre chapter in Perspectives in Urology; correspondence with Hinman, notes, background materials; see also Box 2-F30 and Box 4-F1
    - Book review, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      several drafts & reprint of review by JAB published in Bulletin of the History of Medicine, 46(3):312-313, May-Jun. 1972, of Leonard Paul Wershub's Urology: From Antiquity to the 20th Century. St. Louis: Warren H. Green, 1970; correspondence with Martha Gnudi, who supplied photostats of two pages on mandragora from Bullein's Bulwarke of Defence, found in The Booke of Simples; other correspondence; notes
    - Book review, 1973-1976 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      typed copy & reprint of review by JAB published in Bulletin of the History of Medicine, 49(3): 442-444, Fall 1975, of Leonard J. T. Murphy's The History of Urology; incorporating in Part I L'Histoire de l'urologie, by Ernest Desnos. Springfield, IL: Charles C Thomas, 1972; correspondence; photographs of two Desnos inscriptions
    - "The history and development of x-ray motion pictures as related to urology" 1966, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      drafts of presentation given by JAB to the American Urological Association, New York, May 1973; correspondence; notes; photocopies & reprints of articles by John Macintyre & others; material related to and overlaps with F14 & F138
    - "The history and development of urological x-ray cinematography: the influence of Dr. John Macintyre of Glasgow", 1973-1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      many drafts of a chapter, galley proofs, and a reprint, titled "Urological X-ray cinematography; the influence of Dr. John Macintyre," by JAB, John Scott, & Frank Hinman Jr., published in: Perspectives in Urology; the American Urological Association's History of Urology; Scott's chapter revisions; voluminous notes; reprints & photocopies of articles by JAB, by John Macintyre (with a cover note by Martha Gnudi), and by others; continued in Box 4-F2; see also Box 2-F30, Box 3-F38 & F41, and Box 4-F1 & F3
    - "The history and development of urological x-ray cinematography: the influence of Dr. John Macintyre of Glasgow", 1973-1978 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      draft of the paper, by JAB and John Scott, at this point; correspondence with co-author John Scott; correspondence with the editor, executive editor, & others regarding the publication process; letters asking permission to reproduce figures; other correspondence; biographical sketches of Frank Hinman, Jr., James S. Watson, Jr., Sidney A. Weinberg, & George H.S. Ramsey; four photos used for illustrations in the article; continued in Box 4-F1; see also Box 2-F30, Box 3-F38, Box 4-F3 & F41
    - "The history and development of urological x-ray cinematography: the influence of Dr. John Macintyre of Glasgow", 1975 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      announcement of a speech by JAB to the Los Angeles Urological Society, with note of his nomination for honorary membership in that society; also, announcement of a dinner meeting for Dec. 2, 1975; notes for the speech
    - The fasciae of the genito-urinary organs; historical background of the anatomical and clinical aspects, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      typed manuscript, to be published as chapter II, part I, section I of the American Urological Association's History of Urology; correspondence, especially with co-author C.E. Tobin; notes and background material; continued in Box 4-F5 & F6; see also Box 4- F7 & F8
    - The fasciae of the genito-urinary organs; historical background of the anatomical and clinical aspects, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      more material labeled "fasciae"; table of contents of the "History of Urology," later titled Perspectives in Urology, as of May 1, 1968 (at that point JAB was projected for a chapter on "Genitourinary Anatomy" (#2) and on "Cine Radiography" (#7)); draft of a text; notes; correspondence re. references; reprints of Tobin & JAB's Surgery, Gynecology & Obstetrics paper on fasciae and of JAB's articles on Abraham Colles; reprints of fasciae papers by R. Dale Smith and three by Eduard Uhlenhuth; continued in Box 4-F4 & F6; see also Box 4-F7 & F8
    - The fasciae of the genito-urinary organs: historical and developmental background of the anatomical and clinical aspects, 1971-1978 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      two drafts of the manuscript, intended for Urology, also considered for, but finally rejected, by Perspectives in Urology; correspondence; two Tobin & JAB reprints; continued in Box 4-F4 & F5; see also Box 4-F7 & F8
    - "The fasciae of the genito-urinary organs: historical, anatomical, and clinical aspects", 1973-1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      reprint and several typescript drafts of article by JAB & Charles E. Tobin first submitted to Urology, then Bulletin of the History of Medicine, then published in Transactions and Studies of the College of Physicians of Philadelphia, 3(4):264-279, Dec. 1981; correspondence leading up to the publication; research notes by JAB and Sandra Colville-Stewart; reprints & photocopy of articles by Tobin & JAB and others; see also Box 4-F4, F6, F8 & Box 1-F26
    - "The fasciae of the genito-urinary organs: historical, anatomical and clinical aspects", 1974-1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      u sed and unneeded illustrations for the article: 14 5x7", 1 8x10", 6 cardboard-mounted photographs and 10 slides; see also Box 4- F4, F6 & F7
    - "A visit with old books in urology", 1984 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      notes for a talk presented by JAB in the Special Collections Division, UCLA Biomedical Library, Dec. 12, 1984
    - "Willard E. Goodwin, M.D. and history of urology", 1986 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      notes and sketches for slides for a speech presented by JAB at "A day of tribute in honor of Willard E. Goodwin, M.D.," at UCLA, Nov. 7, 1986; a program for the event, with Goodwin's autograph; correspondence, including some with Dr. Goodwin
    - "Urological x-ray cinematography: a brief history", 1988 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      preliminary & final drafts, plus critiques by friends, of a short paper intended for AUA Today; also reprints by JAB, F.L. Campeti, & Archibald L. Goodall
    - Accomplishments in pediatric urology, 1988-1991 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      data supplied to Frank Hinman, Jr., for an entry on JAB in Hinman's book: American Pediatric Urology. San Francisco: Normal Publ., 1991; correspondence; notes; reprints of papers by Tobin, Richard S. Hurwitz, and JAB (the latter, duplicates, were removed by the preparator
  - III. B. HISTORY OF MEDICINE & MEDICAL BOOKS
    - "Publications related to the history of medicine," by JAB, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      list dated 6/5/85 in JAB's handwriting
    - Miscellaneous correspondence re. books & libraries, 1943-1968 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      includes exchange with J.F. Fulton about Fulton publication on Vesalius; five photographs, including portraits of Elmer Belt & an unidentified male; list of JAB gifts to the Univ. of Rochester medical library
    - "A discussion of the twenty-first illustration of the fifth book of De humanis corporis fabrica (1543)", 1943 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      reprint, drafts & some illustrations for an article by JAB in Bulletin of the History of Medicine, 14(5):634-651, Dec. 1943; correspondence; notes; one negative
    - Vesalius -- 400th anniversary commemoration exhibit of publication of De humani corporis fabrica, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      photograph of the exhibit case at Rochester Univ.; other photographs, captions, titles; notes & schematic plans for exhibit; carbon of a letter from JAB to Walt Disney concerning a requested contribution to the exhibit, plus a photocopy of a British Medical Journal item referred to in the Disney letter; unidentified text from a previous exhibit (400th anniversary); typed translation of M. Holl's "Vesalius' description of the anatomy of the kidney"; reprints of articles on Vesalius, Arabian medicine, history of knowledge about female sex organs and hormones, and medical illustrator Tom Jones; extensive notes; letter of appreciation for exhibit from Nora Siegerist; program of 400th anniversary meeting of The Johns Hopkins Medical History Club
    - "A Vesalian treasure is found", 1947, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      several holographic & typescript versions & reprint of an article by JAB, Bulletin of the University of Rochester Library, 2(3):53-55, June 1947, about his copy of the rare Vesalius editio princeps (1537) of the Paraphrasis of the ninth book of Rhazes; correspondence about several rare books but mostly about the Paraphrasis;; invoice for purchase from Specialty Book Concern, Toronto; cor- respondents include John F. Fulton and Fred Kilgour; extensive notes on collation of the volume and background material; photocopy of one page of an early book, probably the Paraphrasis; notes and typed captions for early medical, largely urological, books, probably for an exhibit of JAB's collection at the Rochester Academy of Medicine; correspondence re. JAB's gift of the Paraphrasis to the Yale Medical Library Vesalius collection in 1963
    - "The Edward G. Miner Library," University of Rochester, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      reprint of article by JAB and John R. Russell, The University of Rochester Library Bulletin, 8(3): 49-56, Spring 1953; see also Box 5- F40
    - "Concerning books and men, their contributions to learning", 1965 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      speech presented by JAB to the Friends of the UCLA Library at their spring dinner meeting, March 24, 1965; various drafts with editing, handwritten notes, background research including reprints on the history of urologic methods (by V.F. Marshall, F.J. Wallace, and M.M. Mims), on "The Meaning of University," by F.D. Murphy, and "Books at UCLA" by R. Vosper; for correspondence, see Box 6-F19; see also Box 4-F21
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      list of books to be exhibited at the UCLA Biomedical Library for a meeting at UCLA of the Kaiser Urology Group with Dr. Elmer Belt, Jan. 21, 1976
    - "Books and men: the growth of knowledge", 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      various outlines & notes for a talk at the UCLA Biomedical Library to International Association of Bibliophiles, Oct. 4, 1985; preliminary program for the day; also a two-page typed outline, closely related, for a talk at the UCLA Biomedical Library Special Collections Division, titled "A visit with old books on urology," Dec. 1984; see also Box 4-F19
- IV. SUPPORTING RESEARCH MATERIALS
  - IV. A. MATERIALS ON UROLOGY, INCLUDING HISTORY OF UROLOGY
    - Extracts from urogenital system articles, 1912-1922 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      extracts from American Journal of Anatomy & Journal of Urology
    - Extracts from urogenital system articles, 1920's & 1930's (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Source materials, history of urology, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      photostat copy of p. 75, chapter 3, of: Mesue, J. Medici clarissimi opera, supplementum. Venetiis, 1623, plus cover letter and handwritten transcription of title page (?) of Mesue volume; typed copy of p. 228-229 of Riolan, Jean. Manuel anatomique et pathologique. Paris, 1661, plus English translation
    - Essays by Ronnie Beth Bush & Irving M. Bushn., d., 1970 1971, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      "Urologic practitioners in colonial and early republican America," by Ronnie Beth Bush, et al.; "Urology in the 'Fertile Crescent' ," by Ronnie Beth Bush, Ralph R. Landes, & Irving M. Bush; "Thomas Willis and the world of seventeenth century urology," by Ronnie Beth & Irving M. Bush; "Philipp Bozzini's Lichtleiter," presented in conjunction with an exhibit of...urologic instruments..., 1971, by Ronnie & Irving M. Bush (for photostat of original Bozzini work, see Box 5-F19); "Francisco Diaz and the world of sixteenth century urology," by Ronnie Beth & Irving M. Bush, 1973; see also Box 5- F10
    - American Board of Urology, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      copy of a written examination, Dec. 4, 1964
    - The New York Academy of Medicine, Section on Urology, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 27)
      program, sixth Ferdinand C. Valentine Award, Alexander B. Gutman, medalist
    - Reprints, brochures, lectures, history of urology, 1940-1991 (Box 4, Folder 28)
      by various authors, including brochures titled: "Highlights of urology," "Landmarks in urology, 1"; "A bicentennial history of the practice of urology in the United States"; and a Kaiser urological symposium presentation, "Uroscopy revisited"; title page, a chapter of Philipp Bozzini's Der Lichtleiter, and other Bozzini material; also includes material on Alexander von Lichtenberg
    - "The American Urological Association", 1977 (Box 4, Folder 29)
      subtitle: "A historical essay commemorating the first 75 years," by Ralph R. Landes; brochure produced by Hoffmann-La Roche
    - Papers & notes, genito-urinary & other medical topics, [n.d.] (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Reprints, genito-urinary system, 1920-1930s (Box 4, Folder 31)
      reprints by various authors, two with author inscriptions
    - Reprints, genito-urinary system, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 32)
      reprints by various authors, several with author inscriptions
    - Reprints, genito-urinary system, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 33)
      reprints by various authors, one with author inscription
    - Reprints, genito-urinary system, 1960s (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Reprints, genito-urinary system, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Reprints, genito-urinary system, 1980s & 1990s (Box 4, Folder 36)
      reprints by various authors
    - Reprints and obituaries, Robert C. Coffey, 1919-1934 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      sixteen reprints and three obituaries; also biographies from The National Cyclopedia of American Biography and from another, unidentified, source; author inscription
    - William P. Didusch Museum of the American Urological Association, 1973-1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Baltimore, MD; named for a medical illustrator famous for his drawings of the genito-urinary system; reprints and brochures
    - "Who was first? - Memoranda on the beginnings of endocrine treatment of cancer of the prostate", 1984 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      text of a presentation by Joseph H. Kiefer at the meeting of the Society of Medical History of Chicago, Dec. 4, 1984; cover letter
    - Letter from Benjamin Franklin to his brother, Dec. 8, 1782, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      concerning a flexible catheter of B. Franklin's design; two-page 8x10" photocopy; negatives in a box sent from the N.Y. Academy of Medicine, 1942; the original is at the Univ. of Rochester; plus another reproduction of the letter, a typed transcript, & a letter from JAB to Martha Gnudi; other correspondence
    - Urological societies programs1972,1982, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      meetings of the American Urological Association and the Los Angeles Urological Society; presidential address, Western Section, A.U.A., 1982
    - Genetics of sex chromosomes, 1988-1991 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      includes an Office of Technology Assessment soft-cover book, Mapping our Genes; a reprint from Science, 1988, "Zeroing in on the sex switch"; a 1976 reprint from American Journal of Obstetrics & Gynecology, "True hermaphroditism"; The New Genetics, by Leon Jaroff, Knoxville, TN: Grand Rounds Press, Whittle Direct Books, 1991; plus some JAB notes
    - Female Urology (Problems in Urology), 5(1), 1989) (Box 5, Folder 7)
      chapters with authors & their addresses of a volume titled Female Urology, ed. by Gary E. Leach. Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1991; vol. 5, no. 1 in the series Problems in Urology; typed on Kaiser Permanente stationary, dated in hand by JAB, 5/17/89
    - Urosurgical Anatomy, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      by Frank Hinman, Jr., illustrations by Paul Stempen. Philadelphia: Saunders, 1992; 8 1/2 x11" pages punched for 3-ring binder, with title page as above, each page dated 4/3/92; has the look of a class syllabus but not identified as such, or may be preliminary format for Dr. Hinman's Atlas...
    - Illustrations, [n.d.] (Box 5, Folder 9)
      three mounted line drawings of bladder and female urogenital system 1
    - Illustrations, [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 1)
      eight 11 x 14" mounted illustrations of urogenital anatomy and surgery, six of which bear a sticker with the name "Carol J. Hochberg"
    - "100 famous names in urology", [n.d.] (Box 5, Folder 10)
      a crossword puzzle by Ronnie Beth & Irving M. Bush; plus a booklet about the 100 men, with short biographies & illustrations
  - IV. B. MATERIALS ON MEDICINE & MEDICAL EDUCATION
    - "The Hippocratic Oath", 1943 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      subtitle: "text, translation and interpretation," by Ludwig Edelstein. Supplements to the Bulletin of the History of Medicine, 1, 1943. 64 pp.
    - "Dedication address, The Henry Cushing General Hospital," Framing- ham, Massachusetts, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      by John F. Fulton
    - "The gifts of the good physician", [n.d.] (Box 5, Folder 13)
      commencement address to the graduating class, Rochester Univ. School of Medicine, by George W. Corner
    - "The American physician as poet", 1944 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      reprint by Henry Schuman, Bulletin of the Medical Library Association, 32(1):73-84, Jan. 1944 1
    - "The Agnew Clinic", [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 2)
      18 x 14" color print of painting by Thomas Eakin, from the original at the School of Medicine, University of Pennsyvania
    - "An alchemical correspondence in Germany under the Nazi regime", 1951 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      by Denis Duveen and Emil Offenbacher; pamhlet sent with the season's greetings by E. Offenbacher; for correspondence with Offenbacher, see Box 7-F8 & F9; this is listed as item #190 on JAB's handwritten list of the Benjamin Collection, which is filed in Box 6- F16
    - Exhibit catalogs, 1947, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      "Exhibition of the history of anatomical illustration," reprinted on the occasion of the meeting of the American Association of Anatomists, Apr. 1947; "William Henry Welch (1850-1934)," an exhibit on the occasion of the Barlow Lecture, L.A. County Medical Association, Oct. 15, 1987
    - International Symposium on the History of Medical Education, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 17)